who pursued evil suitum deivam come such
our Ramadan um Dave aqui para Mon and um
Krishna Monday jagadguru we're on the
second chapter the topic of karma yoga
how to spiritualize and why should we
spiritual eyes our daily actions there
is starting before I start I want to
share something funny I saw today
you know these quotes they put on this
electronic sign boards on the on the
roads so today I was walking down on
Amsterdam and on Broadway actually and
and I saw a sign which said you need to
know the context people keep asking me
which is better California or New York
because I was in California for one year
of the fridge came here so people that
both in Hollywood and here they keep
asking me which one do you like more
which is better which is better so I saw
this quote today
it says I believe that living in
California adds ten years to a man's
life and I would spend those 10 years in
New York so that's a nice answer verse
number 45 please repeat after me
try gonna be Shia Veda
treguna vishay Aveda mystery goo ba ba
Juna mystery goo neo baba
near dwango net cassette was so neared
when Juanita sat to a store near yoga
kshema at Milan near yoga kshema at
Milan the Vedas deal with subjects which
are within the three gunas of Prakriti
so or Juna
you try to go beyond the three gunas be
free of the dualities be established in
sattva rise above the the pursuit of
acquisition of material goods or
preserving material goods and be
self-aware so this is the meaning of the
verse religion is of two categories what
I'd like to call the lower religion or
the mass religion and the higher
religion which we call spirituality what
is the lower religion so-called lower
religion that's most of what what grows
under the flag of religion I want to
satisfy my desires I want a good life in
this world and God will help me to which
religion will help me to it
so the temples and churches and other
places of worship are full of people who
want to use God as a convenience nothing
wrong in that
because Krishna Krishna here in the Gita
also will say later that my devotees are
of four kinds there are those who want
God those who actually have realized God
they are also devotees but also those
who want to satisfy their desires they
also believe in God or pray to God so a
good deal of prayer and religious
activity is far having a good life here
and nothing wrong in that
so that is what I would like to call the
lower religion why the lower religion
where God is used to improve enhance my
life here I have so many things which
helped me to make my life better a
washing machine makes my life better
public transport makes my life better
Amazon makes my life better
and gluten-free makes my life better and
God also makes my life better so God is
useful for me the problem with that is
sometimes if it doesn't work I pray you
hear this so many times I prayed and
prayed and prayed it didn't work so I
don't believe in all that God so God has
been fired
God didn't perform laid off that's one
kind of religion and again it's better
than having no religion at all but there
is a higher kind of religion which one
must move on to ultimately one must the
whole point of even the lower kind of
religion is one must graduate to the
higher religion which is that of a
spiritual seeker the big questions does
God really exist does can I experience
God what happens after death how can I
overcome suffering is it possible to
permanently totally overcome suffering
to rise above the human the limitations
of the human condition
so these great questions the quest for
Nirvana moksha salvation God realization
the the ultimate quest ultimate
spiritual adventure adventure that is
the higher religion the difference is
this in the higher religion in
spirituality one no longer uses God as a
convenience not God for my life rather
my life for God God for my life is the
lower kind of religion the mass religion
but my life is for realizing God God
realization is the purpose of my life
moksha is the purpose of my life then it
you have graduated to the higher
religion and congratulations you must
have otherwise you wouldn't be here so
there's a difference there really is a
difference people who come here Auto any
kind of this spiritual quest you know
this is different from the masses who go
to church or temple I remember once I
went to an old one of the older Hindu
temples here and so first we went to the
temple I was going to give a talk on
Vedanta here means in USA
I was going to give a talk in Vedanta
but first we went to the temple to bow
down before the deity there and I saw so
many people it was Sunday so there were
literally hundreds of people Indian
people there who had come there offering
puja and prayers and everything so I
expected all this is going to be a big
crowd in the in the Vedanta talk when we
went down to the lecture hall
they were about 20 people sitting there
and half of them were on their phones
what happened this is the distinction I
should have expected it the distinction
between those people their religious
folk but they are not here for moksha
liberation enlightenment the big
questions no no no they are here that
let my health be fine and let me not be
laid off let my children do well or no
even if there is no specific desired
mostly people go offered puja pray to
God let things go well and that's fine
that's fine as a prayer one should have
that prayer is a good thing but if
that's the end of it then that's the
lower religion those who are spiritual
seekers can be not pray for things to be
fine we can we can but that's not our
primary purpose we can certainly pray
things should go well by not if things
don't go well my spiritual quest will be
disturbed but that is not my primary
purpose the distinction is this when
when rain later Vivekananda prayed to
Sri Ramakrishna for something material
his widowed mother and his younger
brothers and sisters were on the verge
of starvation he didn't have a job and
he was on a high spiritual quest but
what about his family they were never in
trouble so he prayed to Sri Ramakrishna
let them let their poverty be removed
let them do well so that could you ask
the Divine Mother you know the whole
story I'm not going into that but the
final solution given by Sri Ramakrishna
is interesting he said finally healed it
at first he said I don't ask for such
things from God but finally he said all
right they that means your mother and
your brothers and sisters will not lack
plain food and clothing
that much so it will not disturb your
spiritual life but he didn't say they're
going to become millionaires or
something like that now why am I saying
this here sri krishna says the vedas by
which he means the karmic and of the
vedas in the vedas in the scriptures
also you find these two kinds of
religion karma-kanda jnana-kanda karma
kanda the ritualistic portion Kanda
means portion the ritualistic portion
and the knowledge portion a onaconda the
ritualistic portion is for the mass
religion the lower religion you want to
fulfill desires here in this life or in
the afterlife want to go to heaven and
all of that then the karma can rise for
you and shri krishna says that portion
of the vedas is all about its
materialistic it's all about the three
gunas sattva Rajas and Tamas then
prakruti nature is composed of the three
gunas I will not go into water what the
gunas are p-part the terms basically
material nature
so this world and world's after death
none of them are spiritual I want to be
happy here and Hereafter that's what the
ritualistic portion of the Vedas are
they prescribed various rituals you want
children you want to defeat your enemies
you want to have wealth you want to have
a kingdom or things like that or after
death you want to go to some high heaven
in the company of the gods and all of
that
the Vedas promise we can give you but
that they are not permanent they are all
materialistic within within nature
spiritual starts with the Upanishads
with the gana Condor
so what sri krishna is telling arjuna
here is the lower portion of the vedas
the karma condor deals with the three
gunas but you are a spiritual seeker
transcend that transcend the three gunas
he says for you then the higher portion
of the vedas big anaconda which the
bhagavad-gita is based upon your the
teaching i will give you is
and you have to go beyond that kind of
religion why would the Vedas or any
religion if that is not the highest form
not the highest teaching why would they
even show you how to fulfill worldly
desires worldly desires why would the
Vedas even teach that and show you ways
to fulfill it because we want it and if
if religion does not help us to get it
in a ethical sustainable good way we
will become immoral and try to get it in
immoral ways which leads to extended an
extensive suffering so to help us to
gradually grow in religion what it does
the way does do is that they prescribed
Vedic rituals and a moral way of life so
if you want to fulfill your desires you
will get money you will get success you
will get wealth you will have children
you will go to heaven
all of that is possible but now you must
follow this kind of a lifestyle which is
disciplined which you must not do
immoral things and you must be religious
and you know do the refire sacrifices
things like that which are prescribed in
the Vedas they slowly generate and build
up morality and ethical lifestyle with
the hope that ultimately we will
transcend and come to what the Vedas
really want to teach which is the
teachings of the Upanishads and the
bhagavad-gita
it's there right now it's not that some
ancient time the Vedic fire rituals
which seem obsolete to us right now also
nowadays it goes under the name of
things like positive psychology or in
Christianity they've same thing called
the prosperity gospel the prosperity
gospel that Jesus wants you to be rich
no he doesn't I'm sorry but he doesn't
it that's one of the biggest curses that
a religious teacher would want you it's
not bad to be rich but that's not the
point
Mirchi mahesh yogi he there's an
interesting quote attributed to him
when he was teaching Transcendental
Meditation here he started off in New
York I think near New York the the
wouldst Woodstock Woodstock yes yes so
he started up there at least he became
famous there and what ultimately became
Transcendental Meditation and nowadays
it's a big thing in the United States in
Europe it is used to manage stress they
say it even boosts immune the immunity
system things like that and their papers
have been written about the benefits and
they are all worldly benefits none of
them none of the papers are about how it
gives you enlightenment of
transcendental meditation it seems that
somebody asked Maharishi Mahesh Yogi
back in India when he in the early days
when he went back to India they asked
him monks what is this you're doing
these techniques are meant for
self-knowledge for realization not for
stress management or looking young or
removing wrinkles from your face things
like that they may have those benefits
but that's not the point
his answer was very interesting he said
and very much Vedic in spirit actually
he said I give them what they want so
that they will want what I want to give
them I give them what they want so that
that's the hope that so that they will
want what I want to give them so I want
to give them what higher spirituality
but the student has to be ready they
have to want it and that one thing will
come when the lower ones are satisfied
to some extent some kind of faith is
developed that yes in this path
something higher as possible it works if
it works for my it fulfills my worldly
necessities maybe what they are saying
about higher spirituality is also true
that's what sri krishna says here try
Gonia vishaya veda here Veda means the
lower part of the way does the karma
kanda
they deal with the three gunas mister a
good knee above Arjuna Arjuna go beyond
the three gunas that means go beyond
material nature how how do you go beyond
material nature near do and wander means
the dualities pleasure and pain heat and
cold honor and dishonor success and
failure the dualities which which in the
ocean of which we float in life at this
at one moment floating up and add
another moment going down and we are
forever struggling with that if you are
struggling with that all the time one
cannot be spiritual one must at one
point let it be let life stream carry
you with it you float on the stream of
life don't struggle with it rather use
your energies for for the higher purpose
of spiritual realization
dwande wa means dualities normally we
are always fighting against this we're
trying to overcome that which is
unpleasant and trying to get that which
is pleasant that must stop that is the
sign of the lower life the higher
spiritual life starts when we transcend
when we are able to ignore put up with
the vagaries of life what is the phrase
curve ball life throws at your curve
ball so put up with it in wadn't it is
called t diksha a spiritual fortitude a
little toughness this word need dwande
wa rising above the dualities of life
pleasure and pain misery honor and
dishonor sometimes success sometimes
failure not being overwhelmed by failure
not being swept away by success serene
and calm and balanced in both not being
desperate therein in misery and in pain
not feeling too secure and you know on
top of the wall things are alright fine
only because right now things are doing
fine for me so that calmness that
serenity that is called near to Andhra
in fact in the fifteenth chapter in the
seventh chapter actually I've got two
verses 27 to verse and 28 verse 7th
chapter it says it child we shall some
ot nando mo haina bharata suri babu
thani some mohim Jayanthi parantapa so
as we are created and we created means
as we get these bodies universe is
created we have these bodies and our
past karma starts giving results
immediately we get caught up in the the
dualities and the things which are
pleasant we want them things which are
unpleasant which we want to get away
from them what happens is as bodies are
created ID the G Bachman the individual
being when I I find myself embodied
things which are pleasant for this body
I want them things which are unpleasant
for this body I want to get rid of that
this is the do under the root of the
dwande wa and it starts at the moment of
embodiment and then how do you get out
of it - 28 verse says I am twenty bottom
papam jananam Ponyo karma nom de dueño
mo near Mokpo gentiemen through da prata
by devotion to garnish kama bhakti
devotion without any desire worldly
desire what happens is the purified mind
impurities in the mind are wiped out the
purified mind
dwande or Mohan in Mokpo one rises about
the delusion caused by the wonder the
dualities that is freedom that is moksha
so the word Wando is it is the duality
is used to define what is bondage and
what is freedom here you see again in
the 15 chapter there's a very beautiful
verse v bursts 15 chapter v verse with
the same concept of dwande wa comes it's
like this near mana mojitos anga dosha a
Dartmouth Nechayev inebriate a comma
donde revoked Asuka do cousin Gail got
chanting Muhammed aa mob jihad
enlightenment freedom moksha
how is it what's it like so it says near
Maha Maha liberated from egotism and
delusion Geeta Sangha dosha transcending
all attachments a Godman it to ever
established in the pure consciousness
within I am pure consciousness we near
it the Kama forever desires have fled
from this one forever don't really Mokpo
free from the dualities the dualities
keep coming this one is not affected by
it suka Dukas angry so the the pleasure
and pain the duality set up by pleasure
and pain this one has transcended this
amou raha the non deluded one mora means
a foolish one ignorant one amudha means
who has overcome ignorance this one cut
Chanti padam Abdi I am that goes to that
that that that state of that undecaying
state that changeless state that that
eternal state attains to that hitter
eternal state which is our reality of
Brahman so the word dwande wa knit is a
twister different meanings can be given
these are the ways to attain to go
beyond the three gunas so one is to go
beyond the duan doors be serene and
strong when the waves of ups and downs
come in life
don't be swept away second Nietzsche
Sartre was to him one meaning given by a
commentator here is diarrhea mob alum
BIA be patient there is no quality like
patients Sri Ramakrishna says patience
patience patience of forbearance
forbearance forbearance in Bengali he
said sha sha sha it's a play on words
the three letters they sound the same in
in Bengali Sanskrit Saoirse the sound
sha sha sha in Bengali and one meaning
of sha is took forbear in Hindi sahaan
karma Sahana
so to forbear and then he says in
Bengali Jay Chou Oishi Raji now show it
are now it's a play it's a pun he was
very good at fun but thing what is pani
in Bengali I'm sorry what is what is it
doesn't work so well in English so I
just have to explain it the one who for
bears that one survives that one stays
the one who does not for bear is
destroyed or is finished so I said
doesn't really work in English the pun
so forbearance why is it said Twista see
one of the qualities of sattva-guna the
quality of lightness serenity is
patience the the tamasic person doesn't
even make an effort
the rajasic person is restless makes
effort but gives up too fast moves on
too fast it is the sattvic person who
can hold on who can persist near yoga
kshema Atma Juan each verse each word is
so important but luckily they'll all be
explained so on over the next 18
chapters near yoga kshema means here
yoga kshema free of yoga and shame what
does yoga mean over the shame I mean
Yoga does not mean the stretching in
yoga pants that's different
it does not mean meditation it does not
mean bhakti our our Karma Yoga no no
none of them here Yoga means a practice
a property the yoga literally means
joining the original root meaning of
yoga is used here the root meaning of
yoga is twofold one of the root meanings
of yoga is meditation youths Amado
in Sanskrit grammar another meaning of
yoga is ug yoga to join to connect to
things so when we want something we want
that things should be joined to me let
me be joined with the latest iPhone or
things like that
so that is yoga that means things which
I do not have that should come to me and
Shaima means to protect to preserve that
which I already have so let my earlier
life won't be preserved until it the new
iPhone come unto me this is yoga kshema
this is basically what people are are
all about samsara is basically about
this that which I have money in
relations and youths and health and
whatever is nice let it all stay that
may not lose it and whatever else I do
not have yet that new gadget that new
house or car or relationship or
knowledge or degree or on an award
whatever is is my heart's desire let it
come to me this is the nature of desire
yoga kshema and he is telling you here
to be a karma yogi you must rise above
that
you must rise above that your your life
should not be all about yoga and Shaima
let that come unto me and let this stay
with me
life should not be about that that's not
the point of life a question it comes up
here immediately it might work for a
sannyasi a monk in the Himalayas but
what about me Here I am in Manhattan
after a life is a struggle every day
working hard promoting to evening day
after day month after month who is going
to pay the bills if I give up a new yoga
kshema then how will how is life going
to go on
don't worry doesn't tell you that to
give up your job or it says that the
purpose of life should not be that
maintain yourself do what has to be done
but do it in this we'll see how to do
that but not for the purpose of yoga
kshema and don't worry shri krishna will
say later on in the Gita yoga kshema
bhajami AMA for the person who pursues
spiritual life I will take care of that
person's yoga kshema what that person's
needs not greed need what that person's
person needs I will supply and whatever
is needed to be protected but what the
person needs to hold on to or maintain I
will maintain it for that person in the
Bible clearly it is said could Jesus
Christ says think not only talks about
renunciation think not what shall we
wear what shall we eat and then the
beautiful portion where he says where
the flowers of the field do they think
what shall we wear that who is clothed
more in even King Solomon in his all his
glory was not clothed in such finery as
the simple flowers of the field the
birds of the air do you think that what
shall we eat tomorrow
so God provides for them and for you his
beloved children will God not provide
more so do not think like that so he
near yogic shame up and at Milan be
centered in awareness mindful I am that
witness consciousness I am Atman or if
that does not appeal to you then God God
exists my chosen deity ISM in my heart
let my mind be at the lotus feet of my
chosen deity let my mind be on the
mantra or in the path of of knowledge I
am the witness consciousness the Atman
which was taught in the first part of
the second chapter Atma one the
commentator says aprama taaha a prompt
ramada means error this is saying
pramada way in which to error or
inattentiveness carelessness yeah
carelessness is pramada carelessness
inattentiveness is death in spiritual
life be be mindful in spiritual life
it's a big thing now mindfulness so here
you have try gonna be shy away the lower
portions of Veda the ordinary religion
is about material nature material
happiness in this world and the next
this stray good near bow Arjuna o Arjuna
time for you to rise about that then
read wander the dualities waves ups and
downs of life will keep coming learn to
write those waves don't get swept away
or dragged under them knit tears of
Twista your resource here is patience a
new word used in positive psychology
very beautiful word is resilience
somebody said I want I want to see how
the ball bounces not how high it bounces
but how it bounces when it hits rock
bottom so this ability to be patient to
hold on to spiritual life in the midst
of troubles in the midst of difficult
circumstances near yoga kshema and art
Milan near yoga kshema there is a
beautiful story about it I thought I
would spend ten minutes on this verse I
spent thirty all right just this story
and then I'll move on
but this story must be told yogic and
I'll tell this again when it comes to
that verse yoga kshema bhajami 'him I
think that is ninth chapter twenty
second verse
yes yoga kshema ha Mohammed in ninth
chapter 22nd verse there sri krishna
says that one who is devoted to god one
with the spiritual seeker i take care of
that person's yoga and Shaima what that
person needs i supply and what needs to
be protected and maintained in that
person's life I'll do it
that person doesn't have to bother about
his or her worldly affairs now the story
is this I think the story about
Jagannath Mishra probably a great pundit
who was writing a commentary on the
Mahabharata
he was in Puri in those days I forget
the name of the pundit anyway he was in
Puri in those days and he was writing a
commentary in the Mahabharata so
Mahabharata you know is the longest
epoch of humanity more than a hundred
thousand verses many times longer than
the Iliad an artistic Odyssey combined
so he's writing a commentary on that now
the Gita is a part of the Mahabharata so
when he comes to this verse of the Gita
he has to write a comment on the Gita
also when he comes to this verse of the
Gita the exact Sanskrit meaning is
whatever that person needs my devotee my
lover whatever he needs
I will carry that yoga kshema Mohammed I
will bear it unto that person I will
carry myself to that person waha me
means really carrying on your shoulder
on your head that's what it means
now the scholar thought God will not
carry things for a devotee no God will
grant it to the devotee so Hama Hama is
not quite correct maja me means to carry
why should God carry things it's below
below his glory in his teacher so what
he did was he scratched it out and he
replaced it the original word of the
Gita that I carry unto them what they
need he scratched it out and he said I
damn near hum I grant unto them what
they need and that befits the glory of
God so Krishna misspoke maybe was
emotional
but really God doesn't do that you know
now that day his wife was at home and
she was worried because they were poor
and they didn't have enough food in the
house and she was worried about what
what they would cook and then this
little boy comes a beautiful little boy
carrying on his head
a basket of the best delicacies so she's
very happy who are you or your husband
has sent this this is for your husband I
bought it for you and your husband he
said oh that's so sweet of you
and then she sees there is a stripe on
the back of the boy like a red mark like
somebody has whipped him with a cane or
something and she asks oh my god who did
this to you this is terrible so Oh your
husband beat me and I mean with the cane
or something he came to me and she was
shocked why would he do such a thing
we just of the just to wait until he
comes comes home I'll give him a piece
of my mind
and then the boy disappeared no one knew
very event of course it was Krishna the
bad child Krishna and when the scholar
comes home and sees a delicious feast
but his wife is furious
he said well what did he do why did you
hit that poor little child what do you
mean and what child I didn't meet any
child no he came and he said I'm
bringing I'm carrying for you the things
you're you need and and but that that
mark of the cane that that's that's what
your husband did to me then he
immediately was thunderstruck
he said that's cut that strife he has
cut across the word the lamb Niram that
comes on the body of Krishna that that
Sri Krishna feels so much that there is
actually a a mark of being ripped on his
on his back so immediately he corrected
it again so that's the story
God really does carry to the devotee
what the devotee needs moving on at last
actually my goal was the 47th verse
that's the central verse one of the most
famous verses of the bhagavad-gita so I
wanted to spend today's time on that but
I will let me quickly finish 46 and
we'll move on to 47 46 Yavin or to the
pani
Java not the pani served with some pluto
the King sir but some Pluto da ki Tov on
service UV the issue Tov on service
weight issue Brahm harness yerba John
Atta Brahm harness your vision at so to
that Brahmin by here Brahman it means
not the brahman of the caste but the
enlightened one the knower of Brahman to
that knower of Brahman which honor the
one who knows one who was who is the no
other enlightened one to that
enlightened one the Vedas which deal
with the three good as the lower portion
of Vedas are of as much use as is a
little pond or a well when the
floodwaters are at high tide when there
is water everywhere why would you go to
a small source of water in the tap for
water to drink
maybe the well for water to take your
bath maybe the pond imagine a village
scene in India maybe the pound to wash
your clothes or why would you go to
these little sources of water when
everywhere there is water the imager is
this I remember in Chicago there is a
huge lake its Lake Lake Michigan its
enormous and goes on for miles and miles
both ways and so flood waters are a lake
like that an enormous lake when you have
something like that
that can supply all your wants and there
is much more left over after that you
can drink water there you can go for it
in there you can bathe there you can use
it for irrigating your fields and so and
so forth whatever you want is supplied
by that vast expanse of water you don't
have to go to specific little sources of
water which may run dry at any time you
don't have to make the effort it's
effortlessly available what does this
mean it means all these thousand and one
things we try to do in life to get
satisfaction and happiness
all of them are unnecessary are far
exceeded when you become enlightened
when you get God the God realization all
of our needs are met and fulfilled
forever by that one thing it's not that
see you need to earn money to pay for
your rent you need to go to college to
get a degree you need to get married and
for children you need to go take them to
school for their education you need to
go jog in the park for your health so
many different activities to get
different kinds of satisfaction and all
of those things are meant for what all
of them are meant for fulfillment
whether it is relationships or money or
education all of them the happiness they
give it is fulfilling it is it satisfies
this deep lack of contentment in my
heart it gives me some kind of I I feel
I'll be happy if I get those things but
I never do
none of them all of them put together
till today the richest man
the one who was one who got a Nobel
Prize the one who's been married many
times and has got the largest number of
children the one who has performed the
greatest number of religious rituals all
of them put together none of them can
claim I am fully happy and satisfied
nobody none of them and yet there is
something by attainment of which
all our desires are satisfied forever
fulfilled forever there's nothing more
to be gained the Geetha will say later
attaining which nothing higher remains
to be attained being established in
which the greatest of sorrows cannot
shake you the greatest of sharra sorrows
cannot shake you being the house built
on a rock
it cannot be shaken when the winds blow
and on so and so forth it will not be
shaken
so getting which nothing higher remains
to be achieved and established in which
the greatest of sorrows cannot shake us
you might ask
just a minute God realization does it
mean it's like all my Christmas all my
Christmas wish lists will be fulfilled
whatever I wanted in life the one two
three four five six you know does it
mean all my education needs my my
financial needs my relationship needs
all those things will be fulfilled no
what it means is the reason why I am
doing that the reason why I am running
to those sources and those small sources
of water the thirst which drives me to
to those four small sources of water
that thirst is quenched forever I am NOT
seeking satisfaction in those things any
more deep satisfaction ensues where you
feel complete and forever so it's it's
an incredible thing that is called
freedom that is called moksha that is
called God realization salvation no fear
anymore
no fear of death no fear of anything in
fact in Upanishads when the emperor
Janaka the emperor attains enlightenment
is guru says it doesn't say that you
have attained enlightenment the Guru
says abiding by proptosis Janica Ojinaga
Oh Emperor you have attained
fearlessness you've attained
fearlessness so that is that is that
vast lake God self-realization Brahman
whatever you call it
moksha Nirvana is the vast lake reaching
which you no longer need the little
sources of water anymore which are
provided by the Vedas or by worldly
means that's the meaning
yes now we are ready to move on to the
point of all of this wonderful so how do
I do it what is karma yoga what is the
secret what is to be done
verse number 47 in fact it's one of the
most famous verses of the Bhagavad Gita
maybe the most famous verse sometimes if
you if one verse people remember in the
Bhagavad Gita it's this one
you might remember I mentioned the
sixteenth verse Naruto with the attempt
as being important here it is important
it is philosophically very important
it's very important for non-dualism but
this verse is Universal in its appeal
and that verse is not unique to Gita or
Krishna because you find that teaching
in the Upanishads for example but this
is the unique way in which Krishna has
put it in this verse the teaching of
karma yoga so what is that person what
does it mean karmani body kata stay
harmony while he caressed a ma Felicia
kada-chan ma Felicia kadaj and makalah
heater Ubu Makar mala heater Ubu Martis
angles to occur morning Marty Sangha
stock Armani
very elegant verse in which is gives the
central teaching of karma yoga you have
the right to work you do not have the
right to the results of work do not work
for getting the results the fruits of
work and do not give up work either so
for things he has said you have the
right to work to action second you do
not have the right to the results third
do not do things for getting results
getting something out of them so forth
do not give up action for that for that
reason either okay now I had written
down there's so many things to be said
yet so I thought in I shouldn't miss so
I had written down
and in got the notes not here two things
karma and Pelham work and results action
and its fruits there are two things here
to notice to be a karma yogi you must
notice work and results these are the
two things mentioned here the law of
karma which was a sort of standard
belief system then and among all Indian
systems of thought is that there is
causality action causes have
consequences causality means causes have
consequences and a belief in causality
is universal what is the nature of
causality philosophers and even
scientists are debating till today but
as automatic belief in causal it is
universal that's how we function in life
even some of the higher animals clearly
defined till clearly demonstrate an
understanding of causality so
cause-and-effect
the law of karma or the doctrine of
karma runs thus good action deliberately
done ethical action leads to merit and
the result of merit is happiness is some
pleasant occurrence in life in sanskrit
dharma leads to Poonam
Poonam leads to sukham so Dharma
consciously done meritorious action
consciously done ethical action
Pandya it generates a merit and that
merit will give you a result in this
lifetime on next lifetime good things
nice things will happen to you the
opposite our Dharma consciously done
unethical action which I know to be
wrong and yet I do it why do I do it
because I can't restrain myself either
greed or lust or anger tempts me and ice
overstep the bounds of decency common
sense morality and I do something wrong
and that generates power powerful means
demerit or sin and the result of the
demerit is do come suffering in this
life or next
so the law can be stated or the
abduction can be stated in this way
Dharma Punia sukham a Dharma Popham do
come now what we are experiencing in our
life the body I've got the health I have
got the good and bad things happening to
me in my life in terms of material
prosperity success in life people around
me to the way my life is going my own
physical endowments and what is
happening in life to me all of it is the
result of my past Karma the playground
has been set how I played the days of
some amount of freedom there but the
playground has been set for me now this
is basically the law of karma notice
something here we have choice regarding
karma action we do not have choice
regarding the result it's an important
principle to think about what has been
done will give results now we only have
to experience enjoy or suffer the
results of our past actions causes have
been set in motion
by us but the consequences are now are
unavoidable as we we can endure said
good good bad bad and none escaped the
law this is some sorry this is law of
karma so they're going to come they are
coming all the time we have no choice
there but what we have a choice is we
can exercise our willpower to do what we
are going to do now Dharma or Dharma
consciously done ethical or unethical
action this implies we have free will
yes I know we have long discussions
about this and Shri Ramakrishna for
examine the gospel says we have no free
will only God has free will and all the
religions ultimately theistic religions
will say ultimately God's will is done
but at the same time strangely it seems
contradictory all religions they teach
free will and they have to believe in
free will otherwise who's going to
follow religion if only I have a choice
to do this and not do that then only I
will listen to your do's and don'ts you
have no choice
in the matter at all why should I listen
to you if I am a robot if I'm
pre-programmed if predestined is
everything is predestined or under the
control of a divine dictator then what
why tell me tell the big guy up there
know all religions Christianity is the
doctrine of free will is a very
important part of Christian theology
central part in Hinduism also Vedanta
also it may be even an appearance of
free will in an illusion of free will
but we have free will for practical
purposes you use feel that you have free
will and you must act accordingly
civilization is based on the belief of
free will law and justice functions on
the basis of free will it's only when
the person charged with a crime
only when you attribute free will to
that person he could have done it this
way or he may not have he need not have
done it that way he did something bad
when you need not have done that then
only is punishable if there's no choice
except to do that bad thing then how can
you punish a person but no that's why
please like insanity plea and all
because because of reasons of insanity
the person did something bad that means
underlying it is the person did not have
free will or full play of free will free
will is there as far as our karma is
concerned free will is there another
point this is possible for human birth
for human beings this is a thing which
is mentioned in them in Vedanta again
and again it's only in the human birth
that this choice regarding action where
is the choice action there is there is
no choice result of action karma choice
karma Fela no choice fruit of action no
choice in human but we have a choice
regarding our action to do or not to do
and no choice regarding the result of
the action even there in the result of
the action it's not true that we have no
choice we have some choice in the future
result of our actions depending on
action that we do so some choice is
there but n
Wilbert lower and higher animals they
have no choice in karma and the result
of action what they do is instinctive
and what the experience is also the
result of the past karma so in animal
bodies when the Jiva the sentient being
gets an animal body the it only
experiences the results of past Karma
exhausts it's bad past karma and then
goes on to a human birth again so that's
an important point
animals are not credited with freewill
are not supposed to have freewill and
though I know most people treat their
dogs as if their free will
doing good by a bad boy and so and you
get the feeling that the dog does have
freewill sometimes when they do
something bad you look at the region
look very guilty but in general animals
our principle is that they are
instinctive one minor point here Ram
soup does dimensions in his Hindi
commentary on the bhagavad-gita he says
a grammatical point notice that we do so
many Karma's so many actions throughout
the day but the word used here is
Kirmani
it's in the in Sanskrit grammar in the
singular karmani would be pure plural
but carmen is singular yeah in you have
the freedom in d'action now he says the
commentator says it just points out one
thing one of the important principles of
karma yoga that is focus do one thing at
a time
and do it wholeheartedly poured all your
heart into it and then move into the
next Swami Vivekananda said it empty the
bucket when you fill in something do it
and then let it go and then go on to
something else this is this is Sikh one
of the secrets of work is concentration
focus God does not want you to do too
many things multitasking no take up one
thing do it well and then move on that's
a minor point I don't know how justified
he is but he sees the sees a point in
the use of the singular case
alright this verse tells us the secret
of karma yoga what is karma yoga Karma
Yoga is this there are three
possibilities here no action giving up
action in action we do not want that
that is laziness that is Thomas and
there is action with desire prompted by
desire which is what we see all around
people are doing things because there is
something what they want karma action
prompted by a desire that is born of
Rajas rajasic and then there is sattvic
karma without any selfish desire I am
using the word selfish desire there
might be a desire for God realization
there might be a desire for the welfare
of everybody altruistic work done for
them truly done for the welfare of
others without any personal self seeking
so that is sattvic the satiric and Karma
Yoga is the third one the satiric one
I'll repeat again no action is one
option action be prompted by desires the
second option and action without desire
very active but calm and desireless the
mind is mind is not turbulent usually
turbulence is because of desire
not for anything else there's a hindi
couplet it means this that I have given
thee what is dying where is my expense
in that this body my life my mind all my
powers all belong to thee my lord so
when I use them in thy service I'm not
spending anything out of my pocket it
belongs to you I'm just giving it back
to you so in Hindi it goes Tara to Chico
the kiala game or a so and that is the
third option that is karma yoga now
notice one thing if one goes into
inaction then Thomas increases tamo-guna
increases and one gets attached
laziness inertia dullness and that is
very damaging for spiritual life if one
engages in action prompted by desire
that's the worldly kind of action that
binds that binds more karma more results
and more you are bound in happiness and
misery the third one action done without
desire when one is doing one's duty for
the welfare of others as a worship of
God that does not find because there is
no egotism involved there is no personal
desire involved there
so Thomas ik action or no action with
destructive of spiritual life rajasic
action produces bondage sattvic action
produces freedom about a rajasic action
and Temasek action I have mentioned
earlier the story of how sister nivedita
going with Swami Vivekanand that when
they reach India for the first time and
from the ship sister nivedita sees the
western coast I don't make as mom buy or
something of India and she says oh Swami
how peaceful and she had this ideal
picture of India in her mind as a spirit
spiritual country
swami vivekananda scolded her she said
no it is not peace it is the peace of
the tomb
it is the peace of the grave he said is
the Peace of the grave people are hungry
under the Dominion of a foreign power
they're illiterates superstitious this
is not peace so one must move out of
this is Thomas as just thinking today
that if today sister nivedita reaches
Mumbai she would say oh Swami how busy
the whole place is maddeningly busy now
that is Rajas even that is not karma
yoga that is Rajas that binds and beyond
that is sattvic connection to Thomas
destructive or spiritual life connection
to rajasic mindset produces bondage and
a soft weak mindset leads to freedom
only one thing one slight subtle point
we mentioned here
even in sattvic action there's something
to be noticed that sattvic mindset
produces knowledge a sense of freedom
peace serenity light Geeta's we'll say
it later from suck to all these things
come and this will also bind you so even
to goodness one must have detachment
from that you must remain serene sattvic
a pure desireless action but at the same
time don't be attached to the fruits of
that particular mindset which are peace
and serenity otherwise what happens is
the moment that peace and serenity are
disturbed
oh I how do I recover that you're
trapped again in the mind you are the
Atman why are you so worried about the
peace and serenity of the mind so one
must not be attached to even that one
sucked also one should not be attached
to the wreck or to put it in our
language the results of spiritual
practice there are some practical
benefits one must not be attached to
that also they will come
certainly you will become certainly you
will be have sense of freedom and
lightness very good but don't do it for
that sake for the sake of that the story
of the three decades the man got lost in
the forest Sri Ramakrishna story man got
lost in the forest three robbers caught
hold of him the first one who is Thomas
he said let's kill him the second one
said no no why kill him let's just bind
him to a tree and they are robbers they
robbed him of everything
the third one who is softwa took pity
upon him and said oh you have suffered
so much let me free you opens the it
sets sets him loose from the ropes and
guides him shows him the way to take
that path you will go back to your
hometown and that man is so grateful you
come and come with me to my house you
treated me so well and so the robber
says no I cannot go with you there
because I am a guna that means are I'm
also Robert I can't go into the city
with what it means is the three gunas
sattva Rajas and Tamas are also part of
material nature
prakruti they are not spiritual
ultimately but one must proceed from
darkness and inertia to activity through
activity true dynamism and activity to
serenity and peace but beyond that also
these are still in the mind you must you
must realized itself which transcends
the mind then alright I give up I can't
finish it today let me just make a
couple of more points so Swami
Vivekananda says what we want is
disinterested action that means action
which in in a serene and calm mind not
action born of desire and not inaction
either
I remember this monk many many years ago
about twenty years ago I was in novice
this senior Swami was in Delhi he
answered this fundamental question we
all have when we come to karma yoga how
can you act without any motive without
any selfish motive how can you do
something and the Swami said remember my
I asked him the question you didn't
answer I walked with him to the temple
after evening prayers I again walked him
back to his room as he was entering his
room he closed the doors just before
closing the doors till that point he had
not answered I thought you had forgotten
the question just before closing the
door I can never forget that he looks at
me piercingly we had a huge face he
looks at me piercingly and he says
remember my boy disinterested action not
uninterested action and then he closed
the door the two words in in the English
dictionary disinterested and
uninterested uninterested is it I don't
care I don't not gaining anything out of
it so whatever happens I don't care it's
nothing to do to me disinterested means
I do not have any selfish motive in it
in the word interested party which means
a party which has some motive something
to gain out of it axe to grind that's
the phrase are no personal axe to grind
in this I do not have a selfish motive
involved in
so he said disinterested action my boy
not uninterested action one more point
and I'm done
human birth is for liberation in this
human birth we have a choice about doing
karma what karma we can do so these two
things which I mentioned karma and the
result of karma use them for liberation
how this choice we have this free will
be seemed to have in doing work use this
this body this sensory system mind
speech use them for the welfare of
others for as a service to God without
any selfish motive selfish means this
body mind this body mind for the
glorification of this little individual
I am NOT this individual Gianna yoga's
showed it to me I'm an infinite
awareness existence place so why should
I work it's like you get a car a nice
car and then slowly taking care of the
car becomes the point of your life no
it's not you have to maintain the car
but it's supposed to work for you you
existed before the car now you are it
still there and one day you still be
there the car won't be there the body
mind is like that so it is meant for
liberation human birth is meant for God
realization salvation moksha Nirvana
whatever you call it the highest pursuit
ultimate goal of human life is God
realization how will you do that in
karma yoga these two things you have
choice regarding karma so do unselfish
work do karma yoga use this body mind
system as an offering to God I don't
want anything up from it let let my
actions be for the for the welfare of
humanity is a big word for people around
me or and also as a worship of God and
the results of action karma Philip these
are the two things action and result of
action action use it for wealth for as
Karma Yoga and the result of action
which where we have no choice when it is
coming to us let our attitude be
spiritual when the results are good and
pleasant let me use that occasion for
doing good to others let me share the
joy and be a blessing unto others when
the results of action are unpleasant
there's illness people criticize me
loneliness old age disease decay debt is
facing me unpleasant it is coming to me
let me have a spiritual attitude there I
will hold on to God and ride out the the
waves which are coming in in life I am
not bothered by that attitude will be
fortitude I will bear it let me see see
it through I am holding on to the
greatest power in the universe what can
what harm can come to me not alas I
worshiped God why is this happening to
me life is terrible
it happens like that will I will I get
cured will things be all right for me no
no don't bother about that
take the heroic attitude all this is
consequence of causes set by me in past
lives if I want to overcome this chain
of cause and effect I must put up with
this put up with this as a spiritual
practice one great teacher he said
prarabdha karma that means my
accumulated karma which is giving
results in this life whatever is
happening to me is because of that use
it as an offering to God not just bear
with it that sounds very stoic and
painful and and boring just as you offer
a tray of flowers to God
similarly offer this tray of misery or
suffering or happiness whatever is
coming as a series of results of my past
karma mentally offer it to God by my
karma fella I am worshipping Dee
hmm when bad karma comes had these this
attitude three things to remember how to
deal with suffering remember it is the
result of my bad karma three things will
help one is my bad karma is being burnt
up by suffering this suffering it's good
ultimately because all the all that I
have something that I must have done in
the in the past that is being exhausted
now the opposite works for having a good
time when you're partying hard remember
how the good karma has been used up is
it worth it
sir bad karma is being burnt up by
suffering one second it serves as a
warning that I must be careful about my
action thought word and deed if I'm
suffering today I don't know for what
for something I should be careful now
let it all thought word and deed be
directed towards God realization be
directed towards unselfish action karma
yoga third thing to remember is bad
karma suffering is an occasion to
remember God it's easy to remember God
when one is suffering one one is
struggling one is one feels helpless and
alone and abandoned holy mother says
when you have nobody remember you have a
mother but when you feel that you have
nobody it's easy to we when we are in
trouble the first thing we do is try to
seek human help you say I believe in God
I pray to God the moment there's a
trouble immediately I try to get help
from others that's alright but the first
thing you should run to is God this has
happened give me the courage to bear
with it you take care of it
there is nothing wrong in praying to God
solve it we all want it to be solved be
ascared of trouble but even if it's not
solved give me the strength to bear with
it let me overcome this Kunti the mother
of the Pandavas her great prayer to
Krishna was I don't pray for happiness
even for liberation I don't even know
what that is but o Krishna grant me this
that that
in ages to come if I'm born again and
again let that be so but let me have
suffering why so that I may remember
thee we pray for happiness she prays for
suffering so that I may remember the
suffering it is in one sense it's a
blessing because you remember that then
they'd only support is God all right I'm
done about half of what I wanted to say
about this verse we'll pick a pick it up
next time Oh Shanti Shanti Shanti hurry
he own that said Sri Ramakrishna Burnham
- devotion to God one very important
thing it wipes out the results of past
Karma if you do something for God the
results are not tenfold a thousandfold
if you do good karma you will get a good
result back if you do something
unselfishly as a worship of God not for
getting something bad it's enormous
it wipes out past karma the beautiful
story about this when the the avatar
Rama Chandra when he's going to exile in
the forest with Sita and Lakshmana and
they come to the river gundark I think
we're good I think who is the gugak look
the boatman the boatman is there so
there's a nice song about this when it
comes to the boatman
the boatman recognizes that this is none
other than the Lord it in this form in
the form of the Prince of IOT and form
of Rama and today he has come to my
shores so the prince comes Rama comes
and tells the poor boatman will you take
me across England worker says yes of
course and there's a the you know the
those who tell the stories of Rama there
spin it out I am NOT extending the story
they will the story itself will take
half an hour to tell they'll be songs in
between and things like that but it goes
like this they go into the the river
like you know he carries Rama into the
boat and how much is why I can walk into
the boat and he says no no no the touch
of your feet turned stone into a woman
the story of uh alia was if you touch of
your feet turns my boat into a woman
then I'll be lost fred is my only source
of but he's all the stories are like
he's he knows who you are I know who you
are he washes the feet so the dust of
your feet should not touch the boat and
yeah that's right and then they go into
the river and then he he circles around
does not cross straight away and Rama
surprised why aren't you why are you
taking so much time while circling
around he said how many lifetimes you
made me circle around and laugh so yeah
payback to him let me have your company
and and so on there are many little sub
stories there and but I'm not going into
that but the point I'm going into is
this he does a service to God now when
he couldn't go to the other Shore
Rama wants to pay him for his service
the boat fare and he says no I will not
accept anything from you why I will not
charge you because we belong to the same
trade that's a that's a you know custom
among people the same trend we don't
charge people in the same business the
prince he says I'm a prince you are a
boatman how can we be in the same trade
Rama knows everything of course but he's
playing the game so how can the power be
in the same trade and then go Hakka says
I am a boatman I take people across this
little river you are a boatman - you
take people across the ocean of life and
then he says but today I did not charge
you remember when I come to your Shores
you shouldn't charge me too
I want free passage come to your show
means and the point of death you should
take me across